The Life Of Muhammad ﷺ, Madinan Period Volume 2
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝
بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
Rasool Allah ﷺ opened Makkah,
the strongest resistance, that Rasool Allah ﷺ was receiving was ended, that is Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
But now, there was another tribe which held prominence in the land of Hijaz(حجاز).
In fact, when the Kuffar(كفار) were questioning the Prophethood of Muhammadﷺ
they came up with suggestions of who should become the Prophet.
They said: Why wasn't this Qur'an revealed on one man from the two villages?
وَقَالُوا لَوْلَا نُزِّلَ هَٰذَا الْقُرْآنُ عَلَىٰ رَجُلٍ مِنَ الْقَرْيَتَيْنِ عَظِيمٍ۝
And what they meant by the two villages or towns is Makkah and At-Taef(ألطائف)
and At-Taef(ألطائف), the tribe of Thaqeef(ثقيف) live there.
And the tribe of the Thaqeef(ثقيف) are the branch of Hawazin(هوازن).
Hawazin(هوازن) is a big mother tribe and then there's many sub tribes that descend from Hawazin(هوازن).
They used to see themselves as prominent and important, just like Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
And there was some competition between the two tribes,
because of the Jahilliyah(جاهلية) and the tribalism of Jahilliyah(جاهلية).
They didn't want a man from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) to take over their land and rule over them.
And this is what they saw coming.
They felt that since Rasool Allah ﷺ has now opened Makkah, we're going to be next
because At-Taef(ألطائف) was very close.
Plus they have a sour history, when it comes to the treatment of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Remember what the people of At-Taef(ألطائف) did to Muhammadﷺ, when he went to them calling,
لا إله الا الله,
how they treated him, very bad, very evil, where's the generosity, where's the treatment of your guests?
Even if you disagree with your guest.
The way they treated the Rasool Allah ﷺ was bad, even by the standards of the time.
And that was a very difficult day on Rasool Allah ﷺ.
So, Malik Ibn Auf An-Nasri(مالك إبن عوف أنصري), he tried to mobilize the various tribes of Hawazin(هوازن),
some of them accepted his call and some didn't.
He was able to pull together a very strong coalition, very strong, powerful army.
And these were good fighters.
Rasool Allah ﷺ heard the news and he marched out of Makkah, in an army of 12,000.
He had 10,000 with him, when he entered into Makkah.
And now he was accompanied by 2000 from a At-Tulaqaa(ألطلقآء),
At-Tulaqaa(ألطلقآء) are the released ones.
We talked about them, the ones whom Rasool Allah ﷺ released on the day of the conquest of Makkah.
These are the people of Makkah, who became Muslim.
The army was large, and Abu Bakr As-Siddique(ابو بكر الصديق) and probably some others said;
لَنْ نُغْلَبْ اَلْيَوْمْ مِنْ قِلَّةْ
We're not going to be defeated today due to lack of numbers.
Our numbers are great and you will see the consequences of this belief.
When Malik(مالك) brought together his army and they set out,
they were accompanied by a wise old man,
a man who was famous, a man who was a well known knight, fighter in his youth,
and a very prominent poet among the Arabs,
and his name is Duraid Ibn Simmah(دريد بن الصمة).
Duraid(دريد) was blind at that time, and very frail, old in age
and there was this conversation that occurred between Duraid(دريد) and Malik(مالك).
قَالَ: دُرَيْدْ بِاَيِّ وَادٍ اَنْتُمْ ؟ فَقَالُوا: بِاُوْطَاسْ
Duraid(دريد) said: Where are we?
They said: We are in Autaas(أوطاس).
قَالَ: نِعْمَ مَجَالْ اَلْخَيْلَ لَا حَزَنٌ ضَرْسٌ، وَلَا سَهْلٌ دَهْسٌ
He said: A fine place for cavalry.
It's neither hilly with rocks, nor is it soft ground.
So he liked the location.
And then he said;
مَا لِيْ اَسْمَعُ رُغَاءَ الْبَعِيْرَ، وَنَهَاقَ الْحَمِيْرْ ، وَيُعَارَ الشَّاءْ، وَبُكَاءَ الصَّغِيْرَ ؟
Why is it? That I hear the granting of camels,
the braying of donkeys, the bleating of sheep, and the crying of babies.
Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف), what he did.?
He brought along with the army, their women, their children, their cattle, everything.
And his reasoning for that is, he thought that this would prevent them from running away.
Because if they run away, they will realize that they will lose everything
because the Muslims will take it over.
قَالُوْ: سَاقَةْ مَالِكْ مَعَ النَّاسَ ذَالِكْ
They told him, This is what Malik(مالك) did?
He brought with the people all of their wealth.
فَقَالَ: يَا مَالِك اِنَّ هَذَا يَوْمُ لَّهُمَا بَعْدَه
And you can see through this discussion,
the difference in perception between the young and the old,
and the man who has experience and the young who doesn't,
and the wisdom of an old warrior, Duraid Ibn Simmah(دريد بن الصمة).
And you can see in it, Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف) aspiring young man,
who wants to make a victory for himself and a name for himself
and he's taking large and unnecessary risk.
فَقَالَ: يَا مَالِك اِنَّ هَذَا يَوْمُ لَّهُمَا بَعْدَه
O Malik(مالك)! This day has great consequences for the future, this is not a normal day.
اِنَّ هَذَا يَوْمُ لَّهُمَا بَعْدَه
This day will determine our future.
مَا حَمَلَكَ عَلَى مَا صَنَعْت
Why did you do, what you have done?
قَالَ: سُقْتُهُمْ مَعَ النَّاْسِ لِيُقَاتِلَ كُلَّ اِنْسَاٍن عنْ حَرِيْمِهِ وَمَالِه
I brought them with the army, so that everyone would fight for his family and his wealth.
قَالَ دُرَيْد:رَاعِيْ ضَاْنٍ وَالله، هَلْ يَرُدُّ الْمُنْهَزِمْ شَىْء؟
اِنَّهَا اِنْ كَانَتْ لَكْ لَمْ يَنْفَعَكَ اِلَّا رَجُلٌ بِسَيْفِهِ وَرُمْحِهِ
وَاِنْ كَانَتْ عَلَيْكَ فُضِحْتَ فِيْ اَهْلِكَ وَمَالِكْ
He said: You sheep grazer, would anything ever turned around someone in retreat.
If the battle is to go well, it will be only men with swords and lances, who do you good?
If the battle goes badly,
you'll be disgraced with regards to your family and possessions anyway.
He said: Nothing will turn back a person who's in retreat.
When a person is afraid, they're not going to think about anything, they are gonna flee away.
And then he asked him;
وَقَالَ: مَا فَعَلَتْ كَعْبٌ وَكُلَابْ؟
What did Ka'ab(كعب) and Kalaab(كلاب) do?
These are two tribes of Hawazin(هوازن)
قَالُوْ: لَمْ يَشْهَدُهَا اَحَدًا مِنْهُمْ
None of them, have came.
قَالَ: غَابَ الْحِدّ وَالْجَدْ، لَوْ كَانَ يَوْمَ عَلَاءٍ وَرِفْعَةْ
لَمْ تَغِبْ عَنْه’ كَعْبٌ وَكُلَابْ، وَلَوْ دَدْتُ اَنَّكُمْ فَعَلْتُمْ مَا فَعَلَ
No one of them is present, they said,
and then he said: So then skill and courage are absent.
If it were to be a day of fine noble deeds Ka'ab(كعب) and Kalaab(كلاب) would not miss it.
I wish you had done the same as them.
And then he said;
فَمَنْ شَهِدَهَا مَعَكُمْ؟
So, who's with you.
قَالُوْ: عَمْرُوْ بِن عامر، وَعَوفْ بن عامر
They said: Amr Bin Aamir(عمرو بن عامر) and Auf Bin Aamir(عوف بن عامر), these are two clans.
قَالَ:ذَالِكَ الْجَذْعَانْ مِنْ عَامِر لَا يَنْفَعَانْ وَلَا يَضُرَّانْ
Well those two branches of Aamir(عامر) will do neither good nor harm.
ثُمَّ قَالَ: يَا مَالِكْ، اِنَّكَ لَمْ تَصْنَعْ بِتَقْدِيْمِ الْبَيْضَةْ هَوَازِنْ اِلَى نَحُوْرُ الْخَيْلِ شَيْئَا،
He then said to Malik(مالك):
You have done nothing by sending ahead the main force of Hawazin(هوازن) to face up, to the cavalry.
So, he saw it, as suicide and then he gave his recommendation.
ثُمَّ قَالَ يَا مالك: اِرْفَعْ مَن مَّعَكَ اِلَى عَلْيَا بِلَادِهِمْ
ثُمَّ الْقِ الصُّبِي عَلَى الْخَيْل اَوْ الصِبَّا عَلَى الْخَيْلْ
فَاِنْ كَانَتْ لَكَ لَحِقَ بِكَ مِنْ وَّرَائَكْ
وَاِنْ كَانَتْ عَلَيْكْ كُنْتَ قَدْ اَحْرَزْتَ اَهْلَكَ وَمَالَكْ
He said: O Malik(مالك) take away the families and the cattle up to the high lands of Hawazin(هوازن),
the fortified lands, in the mountains take them to the mountain parts of our land.
And then meet the apostates, As-Suba'a(أصباء).
This is the name they used to call the Muslims.
Meet the apostates on horseback.
If it is for you, then the rest would come, if it is against you, then you have at least protected your family and your wealth.
Malik(مالك) responded by saying;
وَالله لَا اَفْعَل ذلك
In the name of Allah, I'm not going to do that.
اِنَّكَ قَدْ كَبُرْتَ وَكَبُرَ عِلْمُكْ
You are an old man and your knowledge is becoming old.
وَالله لَتُطِيْعَنَّنِيْ يَا مَعْشَرَ هَوَازِنْ اَوْ لَا تَكِئَنَّ عَلَى هَذَا السَّيْفَ حَتَّى يَخْرُجُ مِنْ ظَهْرِيْ
O Hawazin(هوازن), you will either follow me or I'm going to jump on top of this sword.
He put this sword on the ground, with the base down and the tip of it on the top.
And he said: I'm going to jump on this sword and kill myself, until, it comes out from my back.
وَكَرِه اَنْ يَكُوْنُ لِدُرَيْد فِيْهَا ذِكْرًا
And he didn't want Duraid(دريد) to have any involvement.
فَقَالَ دُرَيْد: هَذَا يَوْم لَمْ اَشْهَدْهُ وَلَمْ يُفَتْنِيْ
This is a the day that I'm not counted as part of it.
Duraid(دريد) didn't want, to have anything to do with the consequences of this battle
and he made it clear, he gave them, his opinion they refused to take it.
So, he wants to make it clear that I'm not responsible for the consequences.
ثُمَّ قَالَ مَالك: اَيُّهَا النَّاسْ: اِذَا رَاَيْتُمُوْهُمُ الْقَوْمَ فَاكْسِرُوْا جَفُوْنَ سُيُوْفِكُمْ،وَ شُدُّوْعَلَيْهِمْ شَدَّةَ رَجُلٍ وَّاحِدْ
O men, when you see the enemy, break the sheaths of your swords and attack them as one man,
meaning all of you attacking the same time.
Rasool Allah ﷺ has sent Abdullah Bin Abi Hazrad(عبد الله بن أبي حدرد) to gather intelligence for him.
So, Abdullah Bin Abi Hazrad(عبد الله بن أبي حدرد) came back to Rasool Allah ﷺ and told him, what he saw?
He infiltrated the army and
was able to see the numbers, and to see the families, and to see the cattle of Hawazin(هوازن).
So, he came back and told Rasool Allah ﷺ this report.
And Umar Ibn Al-Khattab رضي الله عنه didn't like what he heard, so he rejected it.
and Abdullah Bin Abi Hazrad(عبد الله بن أبي حدرد) told him, you might be rejecting the truth.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) that you were once misled and Allahعَزّوجَلّ has guided you.
Anyway, Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted additional arms, for the army.
So, he spoke to Safwaan Ibn Ummayyah(صفوان ابن اُمَيَّة),
Safwaan(صفوان) being one of the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ), and one of the wealthy among them.
He has a good stock pile of weapons.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ asked him to give him, narrations are different, it says spears and shields.
Safwaan(صفوان) asked Rasool Allah ﷺ;
عَارِيَّةً اَمْ غَصْبًا؟
Are you taking them by force or you're borrowing them.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: No, I'm borrowing them and I will return them to you.
Safwaan(صفوان) agreed and Rasool Allah ﷺ, if you want to take it by force he could.
And keep in mind that Safwaan(صفوان) is still a Kafir(كافر) now,
and he's a subject of the Muslim state
and Rasool Allah ﷺ could have taken from him, the arms if he wanted
but Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: No, I will borrow them and return them back to you.
And Safwaan(صفوان) was still in that waiting period
Safwaan(صفوان) asked for two months, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave him four.
It says in some narrations, it gives the numbers but they're different.
Anyway, after the battle some of them were lost, some of the pieces were lost.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ gave him what remained
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ told him; I can pay you back, compensate you, financially for the pieces that were lost.
Safwaan Ibn Ummayyah(صفوان ابن اميه) said: No, Don't do that.
Because I find in my heart now, what I didn't find then.
Now, what Safwaan(صفوان) is talking about is.? Islam.
Now, I'm closest to Islam, I'm beginning to become closer to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And he refused to take any compensation for the pieces that were lost.
On the way the Muslims passed by a tree, a large tree
and this tree, the Mushrikeen(مشركين) used to hang their swords on this tree to get Barakah(بركة),
so that they will get some blessings.
It's one of the rituals of Jahiliyyah(جَاهلِيَّة) that have no foundation, myths and superstition.
But because the army of the Muslims included people who are new in their Islam
and didn't have Fiqh(فقه) and didn't have understanding of the proper aqeedah(عقيده).
They said: O Rasool Ullah;
يَا رَسول الله، اِجْعَلْ لَنَا ذَاتَ اَنْوَاطٍ كَمَا لَهُمْ ذَاتَ اَنْوَاطِ
O Rasool Ullah, we want to have Zaat Anwaat(ذات أنواط), like the disbelievers have Zaat Anwaat(ذات أنواط)
just as they have a tree where they hang their swords and get blessings.
We want to have something similar.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
قُلْتُمْ وَالَّذِيْ نَفْسِ بِيَدِه، كَمَا قَالَ قَوْمُ مُوْسَى
اَجْعَلْ لَنَا إِلَٰهًا كَمَا لَهُمْ آلِهَةٌ ۚ
In the name of Allah whom, my soul is in His hands,
you have said something similar to what the people of Musa(موسى) have said,
Musa(موسى) we want to have a god as they have gods,
because Bannu Israel(بنوإسرائيل), when they crossed the sea.
They asked Musa(موسى) to allow them to have god's like these people, who are Musrikeen(مشركين) in front of them have gods
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ says that Musa(موسى) told them;
إِنَّكُمْ قَوْمٌ تَجْهَلُونَ
You are people who are ignorant.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اِنَّهَا لَسُنَنْ، لَتَرْكَبُنَّ سُنَنَ مَنْ كَانَ قَبْلَكُمْ سُنَة سُنَّةْ
These are the ways of the past, you will follow them one by one, in this narration, Sunnatan Sunnah (سنتن سنه)
you will follow the ways of the disbelievers before you, one by one,
meaning everything that the disbelievers of the nation of Musa(موسى), people of Bani Israel(بني أسرائيل) did,
you will find something similar to it in this Ummah(أمة) of Muhammadﷺ.
The difference is that the evil in the Ummah(امة) of Bannu Israel(بنو إسرائيل) was prevalent
and it has overcome the good and became dominant.
While with the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ, they will never ceased to be people on the truth,
who are holding firm to the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
and this is how the religion of Allahعَزّوجَلّ will carry on, until the Day of Judgment.
Even if there are people who are deviant,
even if there are people, who are following the ways of the disbelieving nations before us.
Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted someone to guard them, this night.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَنْ يَحْرُسْنَا اللَّيْلَةْ؟
Who will be our guard this night, who will stand guard this night.?
The companion, Anas Ibn Abi Marsad(أنس إبن أبي مرثد) volunteered.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ told him, Irqab(إرقب), ride.
So, he was on horseback.
He came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
اِسْتَقْبِلْ هَذَا الشَّعْب حَتَّى تَكُوْنَ فِيْ اَعْلَاهْ وَلَا نُغَرَّنَّ مِنْ قِبِلِكَ اللَّيْلَةْ
He said: Face this valley or mountain pass, until you reach to the end of it.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ told him;
and we don't want to be taken by surprise from your direction.
This is your responsibility. This is your part. This is your duty.
We do not want to be attacked from your part.
We do not want to be taken by surprise from your part.
This should be the duty of every Muslim,
every Muslim should be protecting Islam from his direction, from his end
and we should not allow Islam to be attacked from our end.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him,
that we do not want to be surprised by an attack from your end, this evening.
In the morning, this narration is in Sunnan Abi Dawood(سنن أبي داؤد).
فَلَمَّا اَصْبَحْنَا خَرَجَ رَسُوْلَ الله صلى الله عليه وسلم اِلَى مُصَلَّاهْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ went to the Mussallah(مصلى), the place, where they're going to pray Fajar(فجر)
فَرَكَعَةْ رَكَعْتَيْنَ
So, he prayed two Raka'h(ركعة) and then he said;
هَلْ اَحْسَسْتُمْ فَارِسَكُمْ؟
Did you feel your knight meaning, did you see him or hear his movement.
قَالُوْ يا رسول الله ، مَا اَحْسَسْنَا
They said: O Rasool Ullah, No.
فَثُوْبَ بِالصَّلَاةْ فَجَعَلَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يُصَلِّيْ
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ started Salat Ul Fajar(صلاة الفجر),
so first he prayed the Sunnah Fajar(سنة فجر) and now they're praying the Salah(صلاة) of Fajar(فجر)
while Rasool Allah ﷺ was in Salah(صلاة)
وَهُوَ يَلْتَفِت اِلَى الشِّعْبَ
And while Rasool Allah ﷺ was praying he was looking towards the direction of the valley.
حَتَّى اِذَا قَضَى صَلَاتَه’
And when he finished his prayer.
وَسَلَّمَا قَالَ: اَبْشِرُوْا فَقَدْ جَاءَكُمْ فَارِسُكُمْ
And when he gave Salam(سلام), he said: Bear the glad tidings your knight has arrived.
فَجَعَلْنَا نَنْظِرُ اِلَى خِلَالِ الشَّجَرْ
And we kept on staring towards the trees and we couldn't see anything.
So Rasool Allah ﷺ saw him before anybody else.
And then he told them that the knight is coming and they were still looking but didn't see him
and then after that they saw his movement between the trees on his horse back.
وَاِذَا هُوَ قَدْ جَاءْ حَتَى وَقَفَ عَلَى رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
And then he came, and came to Rasool Allah ﷺ and he gave him Salaam(سلام).
تَسَلَمَّ فَقَال: اِنِّيْ اَنْطَلَقْتُ حَتَّى كُنْتَ
فِيْ اَعْلَى هَذَاالشِّعْب حَيْثُ اَمَرَنِيْ رَسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
I was in the place, where you have given me instructions to be.
فَلَمَّا اَصْبَحَت طَلَعَت الشِّعْبَيْنَ كِلَيْهِمَا
And when it was morning, I looked from top of the two mountains and I didn't see anyone.
فَنَظَرْتُ فَلَمْ أَرَ أَحَداً‏،فَقَالَ لَه’ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏:‏ ‏هَلْ نَزَلْتُ اللَّيْلَةْ ‏؟‏‏‏‏
Did you descend at all this evening?
قَالَ‏:‏ لَا، إِلَّا مُصَلِّياً أَوْ قَاضَيا حَاجَةً‏
No, except if it was for prayer, or to respond to the call of nature to relieve myself.
فَقَالَ لَه’ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم‏
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him.
‏قَدْ أَوْجَبْت فَلَا عَلَيْكَ أَلَّا تَعْمَلَ بَعْدَهَا
Aoujabat(أوجبت) meaning that Allahعَزّوجَلّ will grant you Jannah(جنة),
فَلَا عَلَيْكَ أَلَّا تَعْمَلَ بَعْدَهَا
You do not have to do anything after this.
So, the guarding of Anas Ibn Abi Marsad(انس ابن ابي مرثد),
and fulfilling his duty as described by Rasool Allah ﷺ is an act that granted him Jannah(جنة).
And this reveals to us the great reward of guarding Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله),
standing guard for the armies of the fighters, Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
This is a great reward that Rasool Allah ﷺ has promised the companion Anas Ibn Abi Marsad رضي الله عنه.
It was a very hot day, Abu Abdur Rahman Al-Fahri(أبو عبدالرحمن ألفهري) said;
فَسِرنَّا فِيْ يَوْمٍ كَائِذٍ شَدِيْدِ الْحَرْبَ
Let's look at the climate on the battlefield, it was a very hot day.
And this heat causes exhaustion and it affects the fighter,
see the difficulty that was involved in this battle.
So, it started out as a hot day.
They took a nap under whatever trees they could find.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ called Bilal(بلال) and says that Bilal(بلال) stood up from beneath a tree
ظِلُّهَا كَظِلِّ طَائِرْ
And the shade that, this tree would offer is like the shade of a bird.
The shade is useless.
But this was the climate that they had on that day.
They started marching in this mountainous terrain.
So, it's hot, and it's rough, mountainous terrain,
and they were suddenly shocked by the attack of the horsemen of Hawazin(هوازن) from in front,
and then they were attacked by the archers of Hawazin(هوازن) from the sides.
And it says in the books of Seerah(سيرة).
وَكَانُوْ قَوْمَ الرُّمَا
It says that the people of Hawazin(هوازن) were good archers,
and the arrows were falling on the Muslims from each direction.
And the horses were attacking from the front.
So, the Muslims were caught by surprise.
The front of the army was Bannu Sulaim(بنوسُلَيْم) a tribe next to Madina.
They retreated they couldn't handle the shock.
So, they started fleeing from the battlefield.
And then behind them was At-Tulaqa'a(ألطلاقآء).
The ones, who were released, and these were new in Islam,
their Tawaqul(توكل) and Yaqeen(يقين) in Allahعَزّوجَلّ was weak.
So, they also retreated and their number was large about 2000.
And then it says, in the narration;
فَرَكِبَتِ الْاِبِلْ بَعْضَهَا الْبَعْضْ
Camels were Stumbling on one another, so it was a chaotic stage.
camels were crowded, and they were stumbling and stepping over one another.
So, the alignment of the army was gone.
The organizing of the different battalions was gone and it was a chaotic state.
You have the two groups, who are in the front, they were already fleeing away from their positions.
And then chaos ensued with the rest of the army and now everybody was fleeing away.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was calling them and saying;
أَيْنَ أَيُّهَا النَّاسْ
Where to, O people.!
هَلُمُّوْا إِلَيْ،
Come to me!
أَنَا رسول الله، أَنَا رسول الله، أَنَا محمد بن عبد الله،
I am the messenger of Allah, I am the messenger of Allah!
I am Muhammad(محمد), the son of Abdullah(عبدالله).
The narrator of the Hadith(حديث), Jabir Bin Abdullah(جابر بن عبدالله) says;
فَلَا شَيْء
Rasool Allah ﷺ is calling them to no avail.
They're running away.
Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان); When he saw this, he said;
وَللهِ لَا تَنْتَهِيْ هَزِيْمَتُهُمْ اِلَّا فِيْ البَحْر
The defeat will not end, except at the sea.
Meaning they're going to carry on running, until they reach to the sea.
And Kalda Ibn Hanbal(كلده إبن حنبل), he said;
بَطُلَ السَّحْر
The magic is gone, that's it, the magic of Muhammadﷺ worked until this day but now it's not working anymore.
That's it! This is the end of magic!
You see how these people, who are new in Islam when they saw what was happening,
they lost their trust, in the truth.
And that's it they saw that the Muslims are defeated and there's no use.
Safwaan(صفوان) however, he didn't like what he heard, he wasn't happy with it.
And he said: I would rather have a man from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) rule over me than a Bedouin from Hawazin(هوازن).
So Ya'ni(يعني) even though his intentions were not for the Haqq(حق) but,
even though it was out of tribalism and nationalism,
but he's still had a better position than Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان) and Kalda Ibn Hanbal(كلده إبن حنبل).
When he criticized them for their words and said;
I would rather have Rasool Allah ﷺ win then have a Bedouin rule over me.
So, you can see there was some background sensitivity between the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) and the people of Thaqeef(ثقيف) or Hawazin(هوازن).
Salamah Ibn Akwa رضي الله عنه, narrates and this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
He said: When the retreat started, I was fleeing.
And who is this? This is Salamah Ibn Aqwa(سلمه ابن اكوع).
Remember the heroic stories of Salamah Ibn Aqwa(سلمه ابن اكوع)?
We talked about him more than once.
We talked about the story of Zooqarad(ذو قرد) when he fought the Mushrikeen(مشركين) alone.
We talked about the praise that Rasool Allah ﷺ praised him
that the best of our fighters on foot is Salamah Ibn Aqwa(سلمه بن اكوع).
So, we're not talking about somebody who was, who was weak or he's not a good fighter.
We're talking about one of the best fighters
Salamah Ibn Aqwa رضي الله عنه said: I was fleeing
and I had to garments on me and they were untied, so than I tied them together and began running.
He said: When I passed next to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Rasool Allah ﷺ when he saw me, he said;
لَقَدْ رَاَى اِبْنَ الاَكْوَع ذعرا
Look, The son of Al-Akwah(ألْأكوع) has seen something terrifying.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ saw the face of Salamah(سلمه).
And saw, the way he's running.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said that, he has saw something that is terrifying.
So, the situation was dire, the situation was difficult.
But even though the situation was difficult,
Even though the world around you, not just the battlefield, the entire world around you, could be in a mess.
But Allahعَزّوجَلّ can give you Sakeena(سكينه), tranquility, and can give you a peace in your heart.
Even in difficult times, like these.
While on the other hand, things could be great around you, things could be peaceful.
Nevertheless, Allahعَزّوجَلّ puts in the heart, the exact opposite feeling, feeling of despair, feeling of depression.
So, one cannot judge the affairs by the outside.
But the judgment is based on what is inside, what is in the hearts.
Dear brothers and sisters, if we follow the rule of Allahعَزّوجَلّ, even though we might go through moments of difficulty,
but Allahسبحانه وتعالى promised us that after difficulty there's ease.
فَإِنَّ مَعَ الْعُسْرِ يُسْرًا َإِنَّ مَعَ الْعُسْرِ يُسْرًا َ
With difficulty comes ease, with difficulty comes ease, it's a promise from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And that's why in the Battle of Badr(بدر),
which was the first meeting between the Kuffar(كفار) and the Muslims,
it was a moment of difficulty
it was a very difficult moment for the Muslims, they don't know what the outcome would be.
But what they see with their eyes is that
they're facing an adversary, who is more in numbers and better in preparation and better armed and they were few
In that difficult time even though there was some difficult feelings in the heart.
Nevertheless, Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
And then slumber came to them, they slept they felt this feeling of drowsiness, and sleeping in this difficult time.
And here in the Battle of Hunain(حنين), Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
Even though we talked about the situation of Salamah(سلمه),
and we said that Rasool Allah ﷺ was calling the people and and no one was responding, everybody was running away, after this.
After this difficulty what happened Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
ثُمَّ أَنْزَلَ اللَّهُ سَكِينَتَهُ عَلَىٰ رَسُولِهِ وَعَلَى الْمُؤْمِنِينَ
وَأَنْزَلَ جُنُودًا لَمْ تَرَوْهَا وَعَذَّبَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا ۚ
وَذَٰلِكَ جَزَاءُ الْكَافِرِين۝
Allahعَزّوجَلّ, revealed tranquility on the messenger, and on the believers,
and he supported them with soldiers that you did not see.
What are the soldiers of Allah.? Angels!
There's one narration, it says, that we saw a black cloud falling from the sky.
And then when it landed on the ground, we saw numerous ants, it was like a carpet of ants.
And we thought that, these were the angels that came from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Allah Ho Aalam(الله اعلم) how authentic this might be.
The Ayah(آية) could mean this or it could mean, carry a different meaning.
But regardless Allahعَزّوجَلّ says that He has provided them with soldiers.
And this changed the situation and it changed it in a way that was unimaginable
because we have seen what Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) said, and what Kulda Bin Hanbal(كلده بن حنبل) said
and we have seen the response of the Sahabah(صحابه), whom most of them retreated,
and only a small number remained with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Initially, it was only a few, it was Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) and Abu Sufiyan Ibn Haris(ابو سفيان ابن حارث),
and one of the sons of Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب),
and Aimen(ايمن), the son of Umm Aiman(ام ايمن), who was the nurse of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Only these were surrounding Rasool Allah ﷺ, and holding on to his mule,
the rest have fled from their location.
At this particular moment Rasool Allah ﷺ told Al-Abbas(العباس) because his voice was very powerful.
Rasool Allah ﷺ, told him to call Al-Ansar(الانصار).
So, Al-Abbas Bin Abdul Muttalib(العباس بن عبدالمطلب) made his call to Al-Ansar(الانصار).
And then Rasool Ullah told him to specify Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج).
So, he called Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج) and Al-Khazraj(ألخزرج) were special fighters.
They were strong, powerful.
So, it says in the narration that they turned around like cows with turn around to their calves,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was surrounded by about a 100 men.
These hundred men stood in front of an army.
In which some narrations, the number is given at 40,000 strong and in another narration 20.
Anyway, the number was huge.
100 standing in the face of an army, that size.
Rasool Allah ﷺ was marching ahead,
Rasool Allah ﷺ alone marching ahead.
And Al-Abbas(العباس) says that we were pulling his mule to slow him down.
Rasool Allah ﷺ facing this army of the enemy.
It says that in the front of the army of the enemy, there was one man from Hawazin(هوازن), carrying a very long spear.
And on the top of the spear, there was a banner.
If he is a head, his spear would be used to stab at the Muslims.
And if his companions reach to him, then he would raise it up as a banner.
So, this front of the army, the first row of the army of Hawazin(هوازن), was crushing the Muslim army,
it was just rolling over them.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ is now facing them alone.
And Al-Abbas(العباس) is saying that we're trying to pull back his mule.
Until, Rasool Allah ﷺ had the number around him between 80 and 100.
And this is when the real fighting started,
because in the beginning, there was no fighting.
It was an initial shock that caused Bannu Sulaim(بنو سُلَيم) to flee and then followed by Tulaqa'a(طلقاء) and everybody else
and they were being slammed by arrows from every direction.
But now the real fighting, fighting of the sword began.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَلْآنَ حَمْيَ الْوَطِيْسْ
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Now, the fire of battle is waging.
This is when the fire is becoming hot.
Rasool Allah ﷺ stood in the stirrups and started making Dua(دعا)
and then Rasool Allah ﷺ took with his blessed hand, a handful of dirt,
and he threw it in the air towards the direction of Hawazin(هوازن) and said;
شَاهَتِ الْوُجُوْهْ
This handful of dirt which was in the hands of Rasool Allah ﷺ was a soldier of Allah
because one narration says, that every enemy fighter felt something in his eyes.
And they also had the feeling in their hearts.
One of them, who later became Muslim, would describe the feeling that, they had.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ threw this single handful of dirt towards them.
When he was asked what happened, how did you feel?
He would take rocks and throw them in an iron pan and you would hear all of that clattering sound.
And he would tell them; This is how we felt in our insides.
This shaking, this crack clattering sound, this terror, is what we felt in our insides.
We'll read this Hadith(حديث) in Musnad Imam Ahmad(مسند إمام أحمد) that gives a brief description.
Imam Ahmad(امام احمد) stated that it was related to him, by Affan(عفان) quoting Abdul wahid Bin Ziyad(عبد الواحد بن زياد)
quoting Al-Haris Bin Hussain(ألحارث بن حسين) quoting Al-Qasim Bin Abdur Rahman Bin Abdullah Bin Masood(ألقاسم بن عبد الرحمن بن عبدالله بن مسعود) from his father,
who quoted Abdullah Bin Masood(عبد الله بن مسعود) as stating,
I was present with the Messenger of Allah at the Battle of Hunain(حنين).
The men retreated from him,
and 80 of the Ansaar(أنْصَار) and the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) remained there with him.
We drew back some 80 feet, but we did not turn our backs to the enemy.
These men were the ones upon whom Allah sent down His Sakeena(سكينه), tranquility.
The Messenger of Allah ﷺ was mean while still going forward on his mule,
which veered to one side, so that he slipped off his saddle.
I called out to him, up you get, may Allah raise you up?
He replied, get me a handful of dirt.
With this, He struck them in their faces and fill their mouths.
Then he asked: Where are the Muhajireen(مهاجرين) and the Ansaar(أنْصَار)?
They are close by, I replied, call for them. He said;
I did this and they came their swords in their right hands shining like stars,
and then the Mushrikeen(مشركين) turned their backs in retreat.
This is the description Abdullah Bin Masood رضي الله عنه gave of the Battle of Hunain(حنين).
Some events that occurred during the Battle of Hunain(حنين).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَنْ قَتَلَ قَتِيْلًا فَلَه’ سَلْبُه’
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Whoever kills an enemy gets his possessions,
And this narration is in Bukhari(بخاري), And other books of Hadith(حديث) also
Abu Qatadah(ابو قتادة) says; that, there was one of Al-Mushrikeen(ألمشركين),
who raised his hand to strike a Muslim.
So, I came from behind him and struck him with my sword on his shoulder
until, my sword dug deep into the armor.
So, the blow was strong enough to break through the armor and dig into his shoulder.
So, the man turned around and embraced me, (He embraced him so hard).
Abu Qatadah(ابو قتادة) said: I felt death, he was almost going to die
because of the powerful, embrace of this man.
But then, he fell down dead.
And then the retreat occurred, and I was among those, who were retreating.
I saw Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب), I told him what is happening,
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said; This is the decree of Allah, Amrullah(أمر الله).
This is the decree of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Whoever kills someone, then his possessions belong to him.
Abu Qatadah(ابو قتادة) was searching for somebody to witness for him,
that he's the one who killed this man.
So, he stood up and said;
مَنْ يَشْهَدْلِيْ
Nobody gave witness for him, he did it again.
No one stood up, he did it the third time.
مَنْ يَشْهَدْلِيْ
Who will witness for me, nobody gave witness
and then one man from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) stood up and said;
O Rasool Ullah, I am the one who took the possessions of that man, who was killed.
So, ask Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) to allow me to have them.
Abu Bakr As-Siddique رضي الله عنه interfered, and he said;
No!
In the name of Allah, we're not gonna have a lion from among the lions of Allah, have nothing,
and given it to a hyena from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) is talking about Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) and describing him as being a lion
and Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) is a lion
and we've talked about Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة), we talked about some of the incidents that relate to Abu Qatadah رضي الله عنه.
One of the fighters among As-Sahabah رضي الله عنهم Ajmaeen(اجمعين).
So, Abu Bakr(ابوبكر) did not want Abu Qatadah(ابو قتادة) to lose his possessions, for the sake of who?
For the sake of a man, who probably just became Muslim from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
and Abu Bakr(ابو بكر) called him a hyena.
You can see the comparison between the lion and a hyena.
And eventually Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) took his possessions
because Rasool Allah ﷺ told him: Aatiyhee(أعطيه) give him, that belongs to him.
Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) said: I took those possessions and I sold them.
And I bought with them a small number of date palms.
And he said: This was the first wealth, I owned in Islam.
This is the first property that I owned in Islam.
So Abu Qatadah(ابوقتادة) had nothing
and the first possession or property that he owned came to him from Ghaneemah Fee-Sabeelillah(غنيمه في سبيل الله).
Next Abu Talha(ابوطلحه) saw his wife, Umm Sulaim(ام سُلَيْمْ) carrying a dagger.
He told her, what is this?
She said: I'm gonna rip open stomach of any of the Kuffar(كفار), who comes next to me.
Abu Talha(ابوطلحه) said: O Rasool Ullah, Did you hear what she said?
Rasool Allah ﷺ laughed and then she said;
يا رسول الله: اُقْتُلْ مِن بَعَدَنَا مِنَّ الطُلَقَاءِ انهَزَمُوا بِك
O Rasool Ullah kill all of those released ones, they were the reason of our defeat.
She's talking about these new Muslims, who came from Makkah in Quraish(قُرَيْشْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told her;
اِنَّ الله قَدْ كَفَى وَاَحْسَنْ
Allahعَزّوجَلّ has taken care of us and he has done us good, we don't need to kill anyone.
Al-Hamdolillah(ألحمدالله) we have achieved victory, there is no need to do that.
In this incident you can see an example of the Sahabiaat(صحابيات),
and an example of one of the women of Al-Ansaar رضي الله عنها.
Next there was a group of men gathering around something,
so Rasool Allah ﷺ asked; What was it?
And he was told that it's a woman who was killed by Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَا كَانَتْ هَذِه لِتُقَاتِلْ
This woman is not a combat, she was not fighting.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ gave instructions, to tell Khalid Ibn Walid(خالد ابن وليد) not to kill women,
وَلَا عَسِيْفًا وَلَا ذُرِّيَّة
And not to kill the labors, and not to kill the children.
And this is referring to intentionally killing them.
We'll close with the Ayah(آية) that was revealed about Ghazwa(غزوة) Hawazin(هوازن) or Hunain(حنين).
It's called Hawazin(هوازن) and Hunain(حنين) .
Hunain because it is the place, the location and Hawazin(هوازن) is the name of the tribe.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says;
لَقَدْ نَصَرَكُمُ اللَّهُ فِي مَوَاطِنَ كَثِيرَةٍ ۙ وَيَوْمَ حُنَيْنٍ ۙ
وَيَوْمَ حُنَيْنٍ ۙ إِذْ أَعْجَبَتْكُمْ كَثْرَتُكُمْ فَلَمْ تُغْنِ عَنْكُمْ شَيْئًا
وَضَاقَتْ عَلَيْكُمُ الْأَرْضُ بِمَا رَحُبَتْ ثُمَّ وَلَّيْتُمْ مُدْبِرِينَ
ثُمَّ أَنْزَلَ اللَّهُ سَكِينَتَهُ عَلَىٰ رَسُولِهِ وَعَلَى الْمُؤْمِنِينَ
وَأَنْزَلَ جُنُودًا لَمْ تَرَوْهَا وَعَذَّبَ الَّذِينَ كَفَرُوا ۚ
وَذَٰلِكَ جَزَاءُ الْكَافِرِينَ۝
Assuredly, Allah did help you in many battlefields.
And on the day of Hunain(حنين), behold your great numbers elated you
but they availed you not the land for all that is wide did constrain you.
And you turned back in retreat.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says: Behold you great numbers elated you.
You felt confident, in the numbers that you have and that's where the problem is,
if we feel that we will win, because of our numbers,
if we feel that we will win because of our training,
if we feel that we will win because of our technology,
we feel that we will win because of our arms and weapons, we are mistaken.
We win because of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And whenever, we attribute our victory to anything other than Allahعَزّوجَلّ, we will be defeated.
The help of Allah will not be with us.
Therefore, this is what counts.
It is the Eeman(إيمان), it is the trust that we have in Allahعزوجل, the Tawaqul(توكل).
It is our dependence on Him.
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says that
you thought that your numbers will give you victory, your numbers did you nothing.
And then Allahعَزّوجَلّ says: Even the land became to constraint for you.
You felt that you were so crowded,
you felt that the land is not even enough for you, you had to flee.
And then after that Allah says, but Allah did pour His calm on His Messenger and on the believers
and sent down forces with which you saw not, He punish the unbelievers.
Thus does, He reward those without faith.
The people of Hawazin(هوازن) were defeated by a core group of the Muslim army,
we said that the Muslim army was 12,000.
However, the ones who were steadfast with Rasool Allah ﷺ
after the big retreat that occurred, were between 80 to 100 Sahabah رضي الله عنهم.
And there was a core group among those, who were the firmest and never retreated.
In fact, the only moved forward.
And these are Rasool Allah ﷺ and his uncle and his cousin,
and two or three other men next to them who were guarding Rasool Allah  صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ called for Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار), specifically.
And then he called for Al-Khazraj(الخزرج) and then a called for Bannu Najjar(بنونجار).
These were the supporters of Rasool Allah ﷺ throughout the past years
and they were his supporters now.
And these are the ones, who defended Rasool Allah ﷺ
and then defeated the huge army of the tribes of Hawazin(هوازن).
So, Hawazin(هوازن) retreated, and we said that the leader was Malik Bin Auf An-Nasri(مالك بن عوف أنصري).
So, what happened is Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف) and the main body of the army retreated to At-Taef(ألطائف)
and then they shut the doors of At-Taef(ألطائف).
At-Taef(ألطائف) was a fortified city,
while another branch of the army, a smaller branch, went to a place called Autaas(أوطاس).
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ also split his army,
the major part led by Rasool Allah ﷺ, followed Malik Bin Auf An-Nasri(مالك بن عوف أنصري) to At-Taef(الطائف),
while a smaller group led by Abu Amir Al-Ashari(ابوعامرالاشعري), the uncle Abu Musa Al-Ashari(ابوموسى الاشعري), went to Autaas(أوطاس).
We'll start first with this smaller Sariyyah(سريه), that went to Autaas(أوطاس), led by Abu Amir Al-Ashari رضي الله عنه.
Among the disbelievers, who went to Autaas(أوطاس) was Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة).
Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة) was with this small group of disbelievers that went to this area.
Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة) we mentioned him before, he was a very old man at that time.
And he was a well known poet and also a very experienced and seasoned fighter.
He as we mentioned before, had this discussion with Malik Bin Auf n-Nasri(مالك بن عوف أنصري),
where he told him that it's a mistake to bring out the families and the wealth and to put them at such risk.
And he told them that
هَلْ يَرُدُّ الْمُنْهَزِمْ شَىءْ
Does anything bring back the person who's on retreat.
Anyway, Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف) insisted, and it eventually turned out that the words of Duraid(دُرَيد) were true.
Anyhow, let's see how the turn of events went from there.
Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة) was with this group that was in Autaas(أوطاس)
one of the members of the Muslim army, his name is Rabia Bin Rafia As-Sulami(ربيعة بن رافيع ألسلمي),
he found this camel with the compartment on top of it, which is used usually for women.
So, he was leading this camel thinking that there is a woman in there,
and he's taken her as a captive.
When he had the woman or the camel, kneel down.
And then he went to take a look inside the compartment to his amazement,
he found that it wasn't a woman but it was an old man.
So, he pulled the old man out of this compartment.
So the old man asked him, What do you want to do, with me?
He said: I want to kill you.
He said: Who are you?
He said: I am Rabia Bin Rafia As-Sulami(ربيعة بن رافيع ألسلمي).
And then he pulled out his sword and struck Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة).
The strike was not fatal, so Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة) told him;
بِئْسَ مَا صَلَحْتكَ اُمُّكْ
Your mother did not arm you, right.
And then he said: Here, take my sword from my saddle,
strike me with it, hit over the spine, and below the skull.
That's how I used to strike men.
And then when you go back to your mother, tell her I killed Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة).
I swear many were the times, I defended your women.
Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة) was talking to a man, who is also a descendant of Hawazin(هوازن).
These are clans, that are closely related, but this is a Muslim and Duraid(دُرَيْد) is a Kaafir(كافر).
And Duraid(دُرَيْد) is telling him that there were days,
when I fought for the sake of your people and for the sake of your women.
Now, this is a young man.
He doesn't know about this history, but Duraid(دُرَيْد) is telling him about it.
Because he knows that the older people of his clan would know about it.
So it's telling him when he go back to your mother tell her that I killed Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة).
So, he struck him as he was told, and Duraid(دُرَيْد) fell down dead.
When he fell down, his private parts were exposed.
So, this young man said: The skin which was high up between his thighs was like parchment,
from having so often ridden on his horse bareback.
The skin was so rough, because he used to ride on his horse without the saddle.
We're talking about here a seasoned fighter, who has a long history behind him.
Anyway, Ya'ani(يعني), we mentioned let's look at the turn of events
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), the Aqdaar(أقدار) of Allahعَزّوجَلّ,
Ya'ani(يعني) a man like Abu Talib(أبوطالب) just giving an example of how, we never know how the Qadar(قدر) of Allah turns out.
And this means that a Muslim should always be prepared and ready
and should always ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to give him Thabaat(ثبات), to give him steadfastness.
Because you find that Abu Talib(ابو طالب), who for all of his life was supporting Rasool Allah ﷺ
and preventing any harm from reaching to Him.
He dies as a disbeliever,
and then you have a person like Abu Sufiyan(أبوسُفيان), who spent all of his life fighting against Muhammadﷺ,
and then eventually at his old age, he becomes Muslim.
So, here you have Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف), who was the one, who caused this disaster, on the people of Hawazin(هوازن).
And who insisted on following his wrong opinion.
And on rejecting the opinion of Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة), which was a wise opinion.
Malik Bin Auf(مالك بن عوف), he ends up becoming a Muslim and we'll talk about how that happened.
While Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة), who was giving him the sound advice dies as a disbeliever.
This young man Rabiya(ربيعة) went back to his mother
and he told her, just like he was told by Duraid(دُرَيْد).
He said: I have killed Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة).
She said: I swear he has freed, three of your mother's
meaning three of your relatives, who are older than you.
And this could refer to his mother or his grandmother's or his aunt's.
Anyway, this is the story of Duraid Bin Summah(دريد بن الصمة).
Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) who was the leader of the Sariyyah(سريه), he got shot in his knee.
So Abu Musa Al-Ashari(ابوموسى الأشعري) his nephew came to him and said: O, my uncle, who shot you.
So, Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) appointed to the man, who shot him.
So, Abu Musa(ابوموسى) went running after him.
And this narration is in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(المسلم).
Abu Musa(ابوموسى) followed the man.
So, the man when he saw Abu Musa(ابوموسى) pursuing him, he fled.
So, Abu Musa(ابوموسى) is running behind this man, and is telling him;
اَلَا تَسْتَحِى؟ اَلَاتَثْبُتْ؟ اَلَسْتَ عَرَبِيًّا؟
He told him, aren't you ashamed of yourself?
Aren't you going to stand and fight? Aren't you an Arab man?
So, when this man heard these challenging words from Abu Musa(ابوموسى),
he turned around and came to fight Abu Musa(ابوموسى)
they exchanged a few blows, and he was killed,
Abu Musa(ابوموسى) killed this man.
So, then Abu Musa(ابوموسى) went back to his uncle and told him,
O uncle, I've killed the man, who killed you.
And then Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) told Abu Musa(ابوموسى) to pull out the arrow from his knee.
And when he did so,
you know the arrow must be pulled out.
But the thing is that the arrow has to pointed edges.
So, when you would go to pull it out, it could cause additional tearing.
Anyway, when the arrow was pulled out, bleeding increased and Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) knew that he's dying.
So, he told Abu Musa(ابوموسى), he told him give my Salams(سلام) to Rasool Allah ﷺ
وَاسْئَلُه’ اَنْ يَسْتَغْفِرلِىْ
And ask him to ask Allah to forgive me.
And then after these words, he passed away.
Abu Musa Al-Ashari رضي الله عنه, went to Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه, and told him the story
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was sleeping on a bed
that was made from ropes, these ropes were made from the leaves, dried leaves of date palms,
and Rasool Allah ﷺ was sleeping on that bed and there is no mattress on it.
And when he woke up, Abu Musa(ابوموسى) could see clearly the marks of the ropes
on the side and the back of Rasool Ullah صلوات الله وسلام عليه.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ asked for some water and then Rasool Allah ﷺ made Wadhoo(وضؤ),
and then he raised his hands, Abu Musa(ابوموسى) says until I could see his armpits
meaning that Rasool Allah ﷺ was deeply involved in his Dua(دعا).
And he said, O Allah, forgive this servant of Yours,
اَللَّهُمَّ اَجْعَلْه’ يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةِ فَوْقَ كَثِيْرٍ مِنْ خَلْقِكْ، اَوْ فَوْقَ كَثِيْرٍ مِنَّ النَّاسْ
O Allah forgive the sins of your servant, Abu Aamir(ابوعامر),
and make him above many of your creation, on the Day of Judgment.
This was a great Dua(دعا),
that was made by Rasool Allah ﷺ, for the Mujahid(مجاهد) and the Shaheed(شهيد), Abu Aamir Al-Ashari رضي الله عنه
to make him on top of many of the creation of the Day of Judgment,
what a great honor to be in that high status on the Day Of Judgment,
and that's all what counts, your position on the Day of Judgment,
people are fighting for position in Duniya(دنيا), forgetting that the most important is what will happen on the Day of Judgment.
And that's why they say that the Bedouin who made the Dua(دعا) of;
O Allah, make the best of my life, the end of it, and make the best of my deeds, the last of them
and make the best of my days, the day I will meet you.
They said this is a very wise Dua(دعا),
because the most important day of all days is the day of judgment,
because it's equivalent to all of our days combined, the day of judgment is 50,000 years long.
So, when Allahعَزّوجَلّ will make that day, the best day, that is what you want.
So, when Abu Musa(ابوموسى) saw Rasool Allah ﷺ making this lovely Dua(دعا) for his uncle, Abu Aamir(ابوعامر).
Abu Musa Al-Ashari(ابوموسى الأشعري), he wanted to take advantage of this great opportunity that opened up for him.
So, he said: O Rasool Allah ﷺ make Dua(دعا) for me.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اَللَّهُمَ اغْفِرْ لِعَبْدِالله بن قَيْس
O Allah forgive Abdullah Bin Qais(عبد الله بن قيس).
Abdullah Bin Qais(عبد الله بن قيس) is the name of Abu Musa(ابوموسى), Abu Musa(ابوموسى) is his Kunniyah(كنيه).
O Allah forgive the sins of Abdullah Bin Qais(عبد الله بن قيس).
وَاَدْخِلْه’ يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةِ مُدْخَلًا كَرِيْمًا
And O Allah give him a noble admittance, on the day of Judgment
or enter him a good entrance on the Day of Judgment, meaning to enter into paradise.
So, the narrator of this Hadith(حديث), Abu Burda(ابوبردة) says;
One Dua(دعا) was made for Abu Aamir(ابوعامر) and the other Dua(دعا) was made for Abu Musa(ابوموسى).
This is the story of Autaas(أوطاس).
Now, we move on to the main branch of both armies,
which would lead us to Ghazwa At-Taef(غزوة ألطائف), the Battle of At-Taef(الطائف),
the books of Seerah(سيرة) says;
حَاصَرَهَا حِصَارً شَدِيْدَا
Rasool Allah ﷺ put a very strict, siege on At-Taef(ألطائف) .
In fact, Ibn Hishaam(إبن هشام) says;
فَحَدَثَنِيْ مِنْ اَثِقْ بِهِ النَّبِيْ صلى الله عليه وسلم اَوَّلَ مَرَّةٍ مَا فِيْ الْاِسْلَامِ بِلْ مَنْجَنِيْقْ
Ibn Hishaam(إبن هشام), the scholar and writer of Seerah(سيرة), the student of Ibn Is'haaq(إبن إسحاق), he says
I was told by whom, I trust
that the first one in Islam to use and throw the catapult is Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is the first one in Islam to use the catapult.
This was a siege equipment that was used to hurl stones at the walls of At-Taef(ألطائف)
and the first one to use it, was Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And I say in Islam, meaning that it was used before, it's not like they invented it.
But the first one to use it among the Muslims was Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And this was the first Ghazwa(غزوة) in which it was used.
Now, the catapult, when it fires,
it would hurl this stones, either at the wall or inside the fortress.
And you did not really see when it hits inside the fort.
mean we're talking about a whole city inside these walls.
When this missile arrives in the city, it can hit anywhere it could hit home,
it could hit the street, it could hit the market, it could strike anywhere.
And it could cause collateral damage that is not originally intended.
For example, it could strike women and children,
even though the intention of the one, who was striking is not to hit them.
But it's something that would land out of your line of sight.
So, you don't really know where it falls.
And therefore this was used as evidence by contemporary scholars of the legality of using modern weaponry
that is similar to the catapult in its method of striking,
which is different than using an arrow where you see your target and you fire at.
This is something that is similar to some modern firepower that ends up hitting the enemy indiscriminately.
So again, this is one of many other evidence that is used by modern scholars in this regard.
Now, even though the catapult was being used, and it was fired, and it was ramming At-Taef(ألطائف)
they didn't give up and they had archers on the walls.
And in one narration, it says that the Muslims were within range,
and they were being struck by these arrows.
So, they had to retreat and move out of range and then, the Sahabah(صحابه) use what is called the Dababah(دبابه),
and this was a wooden structure where some Sahabah(صحابه) would enter into
and then they would use as a cover to protect them from arrows
until they can reach to the wall and be close to it.
But the thing is that the people At-Taef(ألطائف) used a weapon against Ad-Dababah(ألدبابه),
they were using thorny pieces of iron that were heated in fire.
So, these pieces of iron would strike against Ad-Dababah(ألدبابه) and burn it
and then would penetrated it and reach to the ones, who are inside.
So, it injured some of the Sahabah(صحابه), so they had to retreat
this weapon was proving ineffective.
When this happened, Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that
the grape vines of At-Taef(ألطائف) which were outside of the city to be cut down
and they cut down some of them.
Again, this is similar to what Rasool Allah ﷺ did in the siege of the Jews of Bannu Nadhir(بنو نضير)
when he ordered that the palm trees be cut down, as a weapon against the enemy,
because when they see that their livelihood is being burned down,
it weakens their morale and willingness to carry on with the siege.
We'll read this narration from Musnad Imam Ahmad(مسند إمام أحمد).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
مَنْ بَلَغَ بِسَهْمٍ فَلَه’ دَرَجَةِ فِيْ الْجَنَّةْ
The one, who shoots an arrow and the arrow reaches its target,
will get one level in paradise, with each arrow you get one level.
That is how great the Ajr(أجر) is.?
And one can make Qiyass(قياس) of this on modern forms of weaponry that could be shot similar to the way an arrow is shot.
Now, the narrator of the Hadith(حديث), Abu Najieh Al-Salami(أبو نجيح ألسلمي), said;
I have shot 16 arrows and all of them reach the targets, so that is 16 levels in Jannah(جنة).
Just like that! That's just how great the Ajr(أجر) is.
Then Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
وَمَنْ شَابَ شَيْبَةً فِيْ سَبِيْلِ الله
كَانَتْ لَه’ نُوْرًا يَوْمَ الْقِيَامَةْ
And whoever grows one gray hair, white hair Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(في سبيل الله) and
Ibn Hajar Al-Asqalani(إبن حجرألعسقلاني) says; Whenever Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله) is mentioned,
it is referring to fighting Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says whoever grows one grey hair in Islam,
it will be light for him on the Day of Judgment.
و أيُّما رجُلٍ مُسلِمٍ أعتقَ رجُلًا مسلِمًا
فإنَّ اللَّهَ عز و جل جاعِلٌ وفاءَ كلِّ عظمٍ مِن عظامِهِ عَظمًا من عظامِ محرَّر
منَ النَّارِ ، وأيُّما امرأةٍ مُسْلِمَة أعتقتِ امرأةً مُسْلِمَةً
فإنَّ اللَّهَ عز و جل جاعلٌ وفاءَ كلِّ عظمٍ من عظامِها عظمًا من عظامِ محرَّرھا منَ النَّارِ
Rasool Allah ﷺ says; And any Muslim, who frees a slave,
then every bone of that slave will free the equivalent bone in him on the Day of Judgment, from hellfire.
And the same thing Rasool Allah ﷺ mentions about a woman, who frees a Muslim woman.
So, this also shows the great Ajr(أجر) of freeing slaves
and this is what encouraged the Muslims to free slaves throughout the history
and probably there is no nation in history that has freed,
so many slaves for, no economical reason, for no worldly reason but to please Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
You find that only with the Ummah(امة) of Muhammadﷺ.
Al-Waqide'e(ألوقعدي) says;
لَمَّا مَضَتْ خَمْسَ عَشْرَةَ لَيْلَةَ مِنْ حِصَارِ الطَّائفْ اِسْتَشَارَ رسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم نوفل ابن معاويه الديلي
فقال: "يَا نوفل مَا تَرَى فِى الْمُقَامِ عَلَيْهِمْ"؟ ،قال : يا رسول الله ثَعَلَبٌ فِيْ جُحَرْ
اِنْ اَقَمْتَ عَلَيْهِ اَخَذْتَه’ وَاِنْ تَرَكْتَه’ لَمْ يَضُرُّكْ
The siege carried on for 15 days and they were getting nowhere
and the people of Taef(طائف) were still firm and strong in their resistance of the siege.
At-Taef(ألطائف) was a fortified city surrounded by wall, so they were well protected.
And after 15 days, Rasool Allah ﷺ sought the Shura(شورى), the advice of Muawiyyah Bin Nofal Ad-Dahli(نوفل بن معاويه ألدئلي),
he told them, what do you think about staying and continuing to the siege?
So, Nofal(نوفل) said: O Messenger of Allah, they are a fox in a hole,
they are just like a fox in a hole.
If you stay at it, you will take it and if you leave it, it won't harm you anymore.
What Nofal(نوفل) is saying, is that eventually it will fall but you'll have to carry on the siege.
But if you leave it, it won't harm you, because they're just like a fox in a hole.
They had been weakened so much and all of the people surrounding us, have become Muslim,
that even if you left them alone, they wouldn't have any ability to harm the Muslims.
In Al-Bukhari(البخاريْ), Ibn Umar(ابن عمر) narrates that
لَمَّا كَانَ رسول الله صلي الله عليه وسلم بالِطَّائِف، اِنَّا قَافِلُوْنَ غَدّاً ، اِنْ شَاءَ الله
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: Tomorrow In Sha Allah(إن شاءالله) we will leave.
فَثَقُلَ عَلَيْهِمْ
This was a very heavy news on the Sahabah(صحابه), it was like a burden on them.
And they said; Ya Rasool Allah, we leave without opening.
لَا نَبْرَحُ اَوْ نَفْتَحَهْا؟
We should not leave until, we open the city.
Meaning, they just came out of victory after victory, they had the victory of Fateh(فتح) Makkah,
and they have the victory of Hawazin(هوازن).
And now, they wanted to get this third victory of opening At-Taef(ألطائف)
and they still have the patience and the willingness to carry on.
So, they didn't like the offer of leaving.
So, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
فاَغْدُوْا عَلَى الْقِتَالْ
Then tomorrow go and fight.
And Ghadoo(غدُّو) is leaving in the early hours of the day to go and fight.
These were the instructions of Rasool Allah ﷺ
قَالَ: فَغَدَوْ فَقَاتلُوْهُمْ قِتَالًا شَدِيْدًا فَكَثُرَفِيْهِمْ اَلْجِرَاحَاتْ
So, next day they went and they fought and it was a very strong fight
and many of them became injured, on this day, Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
اِنَّا قَافِلُوْنَ غَدّاً ، اِنْ شَاءَ الله
We will leave tomorrow by the will of Allah.
قَالَ: فَسَكَتوا
Ibn Umar(ابن عمر) said: They were silent and quiet,
فَضَحِكَ رَسول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم
Rasool Allah ﷺ laughed,
he laughed because yesterday, they said: We don't want to leave
and today because they were injured and in that stiff fighting, they liked the offer of retreating.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was laying siege to At-Taef(ألطائف)
an announcement was made that whoever surrenders, they will be freed.
Even if they're slaves.
So, one of the ones who came down was Abu Bakra رضي الله عنه,
who became one of the scholars and narrators of the Hadith(حديث) of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Abu Bakra(أبوبكرة), Bakra(بكرة) is when you have a rope coming down,
and it's rolling on that piece of iron, that is called a Bakra(بكرة).
And he was given that title on the day of At-Taef(ألطائف) because he came down from the wall using a rope,
so he was given that nickname of Abu Bakra(أبوبكرة)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ freed him, so he was freed after this incident.
And there were some others also who surrendered on that day.
Abu Bakra(أبوبكرة) says that he heard Rasool Allah ﷺ say then;
مَنِّ دَعَى اِلَى غَيْرِ اَبِيْهِ وَهُوَ يَعْلَمُه’ فِلْجَنَّةْ عَلَيْهَا حَرَامْ
Anyone who claims to be the father of someone other than his real father, while knowing the truth will be denied paradise.
So, this is a warning against anybody claiming that someone else is his father,
other than his original father, it's a sin to do so.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that such a person will be denied paradise.
At-Taef(ألطائف), dear brothers and sisters, was the last Ghazwa(غزوة), that Rasool Allah ﷺ fought with the Arabs,
this was the end of the wars with the Arabs.
After that there were small skirmishes but there were no more Ghazawaat(غزوات).
Now, a new front will open, a new frontier
and that is the frontier with the Roman Empire and that is the Ghazwaa(غزوة) Of Tabook(تبوك).
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
اَلسَّلَامُ عَلَيْكُمْ وَرَحْمةُ الله وَبَرَكَاتُه